<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Morbus satanicus. = The devils disease: or, The sin of pride arraigned and condemned The tenth edition, with many additions. By Andrew Jones, student in Divinity.</title>
            <author>Jones, Andrew, M.A.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47014</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830342</idno>
  <idno type="VID">34793</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240895644</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218774</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830342</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99830342e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47014)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34793)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2072:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Morbus satanicus. = The devils disease: or, The sin of pride arraigned and condemned The tenth edition, with many additions. By Andrew Jones, student in Divinity.</title>
                  <author>Jones, Andrew, M.A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p. : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Elizabeith Andrews, at the White Lion near Pye Corner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Woodcut portrait on title page.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Pride and vanity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34793:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Morbus Satanicus.</hi> The DEVILS DISEASE: OR, The sin of Pride arraigned and condemned.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Isa. 3.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Daughters of Sion are haughty, and walk with stretched out necks, and wanton eyes; walking and mincing as they go, and making a tink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with their feet.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The tenth Edition, with many Additions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Andrew Jones, <hi>Student in Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>portrait of a woman</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Elizabeth Andrews,</hi> at the White Lion near <hi>Pye Corner.</hi> 1662.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34793:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:34793:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:34793:3"/>
            <head>Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>There is lately published an excellent and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitablé Sermon, called, The Christians blessed Choice; or, the godly mans Resolution. Likewise Christs first Sermon, or, The necessity, duty and practice of Repentance, opened and applied. Also Christs last Sermon, or, the everlasting estate and condition of all men in the world to come. And the Christians best Garment, or, The putting on of the Lord Jesus Christ. Also Heavens Glory, and Hells Horror, or the Parable between Dives and Lazarus opened and applied. And the School of Grace. Very godly Books, and are but three pence price.</p>
            <p>There are likewise nine other small Books, all of them very godly, and very comfortable for thy soul. One is entituled, Englands Faithful Physician. The second, Dooms-day at hand. The third, the dreadful character of a drunkard. The fourth, The Fathers last Blessing to his children. The fifth, The sin of Pride arraigned and condemned. The sixth, The Plain Mans Plain Path-way to Heaven. The seventh, The Black Book of Conscience. The eighth, Peters Sermon of Repentance. The ninth, The Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Christian. All very necessary for these licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious times, and each of them being but of two pence price. They are to be sold by <hi>Elizabeth Andrews,</hi> at the White Lion near <hi>Pye-Corner.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:34793:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Ezek 16.49.</bibl>
                  <p>Behold, this was the iniquity of thy sister Sodom, Pride, and fulness of Bread, and abundance of Idleness was in her, and in her Daughters, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did she strengthen the hands of the poor and needy.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese Words, Beloved, may very well be compared and applied to these last and worst of times wherein we live; for if ever any Scripture was fulfilled, this very scripture is fulfilled among us at this very day: <hi>For behold, this is the iniquity of England, pride &amp; fulness of bread in her, and in her children; the daughters of England are proud and haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and walk with stretched out necks, and naked breasts, walking and mincing as they go.</hi> I need not trouble my self much to prove this assertion, the Lord knows the truth of it is too too mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest among us in these our dayes; for now as the Prophet saith <hi>Ezek. 7. Behold the day, behold it is come, behold it is come, the rod hath blossom'd, pride hath budded, &amp; violence is risen up into a rod of wickedness.</hi> The people of <hi>England</hi> have listed themselves up, and have prided themselves in
<pb facs="tcp:34793:4"/>their greatness; <hi>the pride of England,</hi> as it was said of <hi>Israel, Hos. 5.5. doth testifie against it to its face.</hi> In the words of the text we have the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet testifying against the pride of the Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, comparing it with the sins of <hi>Sodom;</hi> and the iniquity of <hi>Sodom</hi> you know was very great; the sins here mentioned, are first pride, then sulness of bread, and abundance of idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness: Pride that's the leading sin of all.</p>
            <p>Now the sin of pride is either inward in the heart, or else outward in the body; and that in five several particulars. First in the spéech, <hi>Dan. 4.30, Is not this great Babylon that I have built,</hi> saith <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, for the house of my kingdom, and for the honour of my majesty.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conoly, pride is in the looks, <hi>Prov. 6.17. A proud look and a lying tongue, the Lord hater. David</hi> saith, <hi>Psalm 131.1. My heart is not haughty, or mine eyes lofty.</hi> Thirdly, pride is in the habit and apparel of the body; thu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Herods</hi> pride ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, <hi>Acts 12.21. Herod arayed himself in gorge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous apparel;</hi> so like wise the rich man, <hi>Luke 16.10. clothed himself in purple, and fared deliciously every day.</hi> Fourthly price is in the gestures &amp; carriage of the body, <hi>Isa. 31.16. The daughters of Sion are haughty, and walk with stretched out necks, and wanton eyes, mincing and tinkling with their feet as they go.</hi> Fifthly, pride is oftentimes in the actions, <hi>Isa. 3.5. The childe shall behave
<pb facs="tcp:34793:4"/>himself proudly against the ancient, Nehem. 9.10, 19. The children of Israel dealt proudly, they and their fathers, and hearkened not to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So likewise pride is oftentimes séen in mens curious &amp; over-costly feastings, and pompous adorning of their Houses, more then modesty, lawful delight, and necessity doth require; and this sinne is very common amongst us at this day; now the stufulness and wickedness of the sin of pride blinds and hardens the mindes and hearts of men and women, <hi>Dan. 5.30. Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzars</hi> heart was lifted up, and his minde so blinded with pride, that he was not onely deposed from his throne, but also driven from among the sons of men, and his heart made like the Beasts; he was so blinded that he became bruitish, and his dwelling was with wilde As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and he was fed with grass like oxen.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Pride sets men in opposition against God, in other sins men run away from God, but pride is a comming against God; in other sins men flie from God, but in the sin of pride men flie upon God, <hi>Jam. 4.26. God resist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the proud.</hi> Men do not resist until they are set upon: When thieves set upon true men, they will if they find themselves able make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance; so proud persons they set upon God, and as much as in them lies, endeavour to pull
<pb facs="tcp:34793:5"/>God out of heaven, this was the sin of the devil, which cast him out of heaven, <hi>Psal. 73.9. Proud men set their mouths against Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, pride is the fountain and root of all other sins, Absalons pride carried him on to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliion against his own father; it was <hi>Athaliahs</hi> pride that put her upon slaying the seed Royal, that so she her self might reign, <hi>2 Kings 11. Prov. 13.10.</hi> saith <hi>Solomon, Onely by pride commeth contention.</hi> All the contentions that ever have been, or at this day are, either in Law Suits, or Families, or in trading, or whatsoever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions there are, these do all spring from pride; and as covetousness is the root of all evil, so pride is the nurse of all covetousness: did not mens hearts so much run after pride, there might be more love then there is, and men néed not be so covetous after riches, and so desirous of gorgeous apparel as they are; pride carries men forth into the very heighth of all iniquity: it was <hi>Hamans</hi> pride that put him upon seeking and plotting the death of all the Iewes in <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, pride makes men like the devil, it is <hi>Morbus Satanicus,</hi> the Devils disease, and far worse then the <hi>French,</hi> or any other foul disease: the devil was the first that ever prided it against God, pride made the devil to be a devil, he was first an Angel in Heaven, but for his pride a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb facs="tcp:34793:5"/>God, he was cast down to hell, and so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a devil, <hi>1 Tim. 3.6. Ministers of God should not be Novices, saith the</hi> Apostle, <hi>left being lifted up with pride, they fall into the condemnation of the devil.</hi> Therefore God many times to prevent this sin of pride, suffers the devil to buffet even his own children, as he did St. <hi>Paul, 2 Cor. 12.7. God had rather see his children buffeted by Satan, then swell with that abominable sin of pride.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, Pride is the sin that maketh God abhor men, <hi>Prov. 16.5. Every one that is proud is an abomination to the Lord, and though hand joyn in hand,</hi> saith the Lord, <hi>pride shall not be unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisht.</hi> A proud look is one of the things that God hates, <hi>Prov. 6.16. Gods hatred is against proud men, Psal. 119.16. Proud persons are accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed.</hi> God delights in nothing more then his glory, and he hates nothing more then pride, which would, if permitted by him, rob him of his glory.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, pride is an utter enemy to the future and everlasting happiness and salvation of men, <hi>1 Cor. 8.2. He that thinks he knows any thing, that is, he that is proudly conceited of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, that man</hi> (saith the Apostle) <hi>knows nothing as he ought to do.</hi> Proud persons think they know something, if not all things; but the word of God saith, <hi>Men must become fools, that they may be made wise; that is,</hi> men must deny them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,
<pb facs="tcp:34793:6"/>and go to Christ for wisdom, righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, redemption, grace, life and salvation, but proud persons will not do this. <hi>Ye will not come to me,</hi> saith Christ, <hi>John 5.40. that ye might have life.</hi> Men that are proud and self-conceited care not for comming to Christ; he that comes to Christ must deny himself, &amp; forsake all, which I am sure no proud persons will be willing to do: honour, and greatness, and outward brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, they are the things which proud persons look after, so they may be proud, fine, and brave, 'tis no matter for any thing else; therefore it is twice recorded in Scripture, <hi>God resisteth the proud, and giveth grace to the humble, James 5.5. 1 Pet. 5.5.</hi> Proud persons, like full stomacks loath the honey-comb of grace.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Pride bringe heavy calamities and fore judgements both upon the persons and places where it is exercised, <hi>Prov. 15.25. The Lord will destroy the proud. Haman</hi> and <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> were proud persons, and God destroyed them and their houses. <hi>Herod</hi> was a proud per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, <hi>and the Angel of the Lord smote him, and he was eaten to death of worms, Acts 12.23.</hi> Men that are haughty and proud, God will bring them down. <hi>Nebuchadnezzar was a high tree, his top reached up to heaven, Dan. 4.11.</hi> he was proud and haughty, but what became of him; he was cut down: so Pharaoh and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> were full of
<pb facs="tcp:34793:6"/>pride and cruelty, and what followed, <hi>Exodus 15.10. They in all their pride and glory were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed in the sea.</hi> So likewise <hi>Saul,</hi> he wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed proud and rebellious against God, and the Lord rejected him, and cut him off by the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listines, <hi>1 Sam. 31.</hi> So likewise <hi>Ahab, 1 Kings 22.</hi> So <hi>Belshazzar</hi> he lifted himself up against the Lord, and presently a hand was séen writing his doom upon the wall, and that very night was he stain. Proud persons who ever they are, God will humble them and lay them low: God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth them afar off, he rest sts them, and will scatter them.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Mal. 4.1.</hi> saith the Prophet, <hi>Behold the day commeth that shall burn as an Oven, and all the proud, yea, and all that do wickedly shall be as stubble; and the day cometh that shall burn them up, saith the Lord of hosts, and it shall leave them neither root nor branch. Isa. 2.12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. The day of the Lord of Hosts shall be upon every one that is proud, and he shall be brought low; and upon all the cedars of Lebanon, and all the oaks of Bashan, and upon all high hills and mountains that are lifted up, upon every high tower and fenced wall, upon all the ships of Tarshish, and upon all pleasant pictures, and the loftiness of man shall be bowed down, and the haughtiness of men shall be made low.</hi> Whatsoever it is that is proud and lofty, that lifts it self up against the Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:34793:7"/>it shall be thrown down; for pride must down, as Christ said of the Temple, not a stone of it shall be left, but it shall be utterly overthrown. The Iews were so proud, that they despised the meanness and maekness of Thrist, and openly said in the pride of their hearts, <hi>We will not have this man to reign over us:</hi> but what became of them? They were shortly after scattered throughout the world, and destroyed; yea, <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem</hi> it self, that glorious City, utterly ruined and destroyed</p>
            <p>So likewise <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Ammon, Assyria,</hi> and <hi>Nineveh</hi> threatened for their pride, <hi>Zeph. 2.9, 10. As I live saith the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, surely Moab shall be as Sodom, and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Ammon as Gomorrah, even the breeding of nettles and salt pits, and a perpetual desolation; The Ethiopian also shall be slain by the sword, and I will stretch forth my hand against Assyria, and destroy it, and will make Nineveh a desolation and a wilderness.</hi> And the reason of all this is given in verse the tenth, <hi>This shall they have for their pride, because they have reproached and magnified themselves against the people of the Lord of hosts.</hi> Pride was the first firebrand that set <hi>Sodom</hi> on fire, and will be the ruine and destruction of those that delight therein, <hi>2 Sam. 22.28. The eyes of the Lord are upon the haughty, that he may bring them down.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34793:7"/>
            <p> Aud I beséech you observe, that pride is the fore-runner of ruine and destruction, <hi>Hos. 5.5. The pride of Israel doth testifie to his face, therfore shall Israel and Ephraim fall in their iniquity, Juda also shall fall with them.</hi> Is <hi>Israel</hi> proud? So is <hi>Juda, so is England:</hi> the daughters of <hi>England</hi> are prond and haughty, walking with stretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forh necks, painted and spotted faces, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked breasts, and powdered locks, walking and mincing as they go. Must <hi>Israel fall?</hi> so must <hi>England;</hi> for after pride cometh destruction: Pride struts before, and leads the Wan, but Iudgement and destruction follows after, and brings up the Rear. <hi>Prov. 16.18. Pride goeth before destruction, and a haughty spirit before a fall. Lucifers</hi> pride cast him out of heaven into hell; <hi>Sodoms</hi> pride set <hi>Sodom</hi> on fire; <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lems</hi> pride brought down ruins and destruction upon their heads: Yea, most certain it is, that pride hath béen the cause of all the commotions, wars, ruines, and desolations that ever were in the world. Proud <hi>Haman</hi> he thought scorn in lay hands upon <hi>Mordecai</hi> alone, but he will have the blood and bones of all the Iews to satisfts his pride. <hi>Esther 3.6.</hi> and shortly after he was hanged upon the same Gallows which he had set up for <hi>Mordecai, Esth. 7.10. Herods</hi> heart was swoln with pride, and the worms eat him up, <hi>Acts 12.13.</hi> So <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> in <hi>Dan. 4.30, 31.32,
<pb facs="tcp:34793:8"/>33.</hi> priding himself in his greatness, had his Kingdom taken from him, and he was dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth from among men, and did eat grass as oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of Heaven, till his hair was grown like Eagles feathers, and his nails like Birds claws. So <hi>David, 2 Sam. 24.</hi> in the pride of his heart num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers his people, and for that sin the Lord swept away seventy thousand of his people presently after. So <hi>Absalon</hi> and <hi>Adonijah</hi> by pride aspirs and seek to set themselves in the Throne, and thereby brought destruction upon themselves. Pride loves to go before, but it is before a fall, before destruction: if you finde pride in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of any things, you shall certainly finds destruction in the latter end. Pride procéeded and went before the fall of our first Patents, <hi>Gen. 3.5.</hi> they would be like unto God, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good and evil. Pride procured the Angels fall from Heaven to Hell, and will be the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of all those Kingdoms and Persons where it is embraced and received, <hi>Luke 14.11. Whosoever exalteth himself shall be abased, and he that humbleth himself shall be exalted:</hi> Be they particular Persons, Cities, or Kingdoms, or whosoever they are that do exalt themselves through Pride, God will throw them down. <hi>Jer. 50.26, 30, 31, 32. Babylon hath been proud a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Lord, and against the holy one of Israel;
<pb facs="tcp:34793:8"/>therefore shall her young men fall in the streets, and all her men of warre shall be cut off, saith the Lord. Behold, I am against thee, O thou most proud, saith the Lord of Hosts; for the day is come, and the time that I will visit thee, and the most proud shall stumble and fall, and none shall raise him up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is greatly to be feared, that those three Nations of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> have been proud, yea, very proud against the Lord and his worship, and have greatly provoked him with that sin: the Lord grant we be not punished with fore Iudgements for this sin. God threatned <hi>Jerusalem</hi> for this sin, <hi>Jer. 13.9. I will mark the pride of Judah, and the great pride of Jerusalem, saith the Lord.</hi> And how he will do this, you may sée in <hi>Isaiah 3.16, 17, 18, 19, 20.</hi> and so on to the end of the Chapter: <hi>Moreover the Lord saith, because the Daughters of Sion are haughty, and walk with stretched forth necks, and wanton eyes, walking and mincing as they go, and making a tinkling with their feet: Therefore the Lord will smite with a scab the crown of the head of the daughters of Sion, and the Lord will discover their secret parts. In that day the Lord will take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the bravery of their tinkling ornaments about their feet, their cauls, and their round tires like the Moon; their chains, and their bracelets, and their mufflers, their jewels, and the Ornament of their
<pb facs="tcp:34793:9"/>legs, the head-bands, and the tablets, and the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, the rings, and the nose-jewels, the change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able suits of apparel, the mantles, the wimples, and the crisping pins, the glasses, and the fine linnen, the hoods, and the veils: And it shall come to pass, that instead of a sweet smell there shall be a stink, and instead of a girdle a rent, and instead of well set hair baldness; and instead of a stomacher a girding with sackcloth, and a burning instead of beauty. Their men shall fall by the sword, and their mighty men in the war, and her gates shall lament and mourn, and she being desolate shall sit upon the throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And God hath not onely threatened and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced his displeasure against this abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble sin of pride, but he hath likewise in all ages inflicted his judgements upon sundry particular persons, for their extraordinary delight in this sin. Many and fearful have béen the plagues and most dreadful judgements which God in all Ages hath powred out and inflicted upon those that have effended his holy Majesty here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as all Histories both sacred and prophane do abundantly declare. For proof whereof, take as if were a taste but of some sew, whereby it will clearly appear how wonder fully the Lord our God, in all ages, times, and places of the world hath forely punished all those Nations, Countreys, or People whatsoever, who through
<pb facs="tcp:34793:9"/>pride and arrogancy have lifted themselves up and rebelled against the great God of Headen and earth: as for instance, The Devil who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was an Angel in heaven, who proudly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming to set himself above the Lord, who is God over all, was for this his pride cast down from heaven, and thrown into the bottomless pit of hell, into that lake which burneth with fire and brimstone for ever, where he is reser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as St. <hi>Jude</hi> saith, <hi>Jude 6. In everlasting chains under darkness, unto the judgement of the great day.</hi> So likewise <hi>Adam</hi> through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luston of the Devil, proudly destring to be as God, knowing good and evil, was for this his wilful sin, for ever plunging both himself and all his posterity, into the gulf of woe and mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that for over; so likewise <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram, Numb. 16.</hi> for their exceeding great pride in stirring up the people to Revellion, were swallowed up alive into the earth, they &amp; all that appertatined unto them. So in <hi>Gen. 11.</hi> the people of Babel going about to build them a Tower whose top should reach up to Heaven, thereby proundly intending to seat themselves even with God himself, were all confounded in a moment, and their work brought into confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ston. So in <hi>1 Sam. 17. Goliah</hi> that hugs and mighty Gyant proudly defying the Armies of the living God, was shamefully slain by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:34793:10"/>the servant of God with a small stone out of a sling: So that great <hi>Antiochus</hi> intending to overthrow and spoil <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and thereby spoil and destroy the Temple and Sanctuary of the Lord, and murther the people of God, was for this his pride over-turn'o in his Chariot, as he was riding to effect this his cursed designe, and his beliy burst assunder, out of which there crawled forth most filthy loathsome stinking Worms; and in the end he su stunk, that both himself and his servants loathed the sight and savour of his most loathsome carkass; and thus ended this proud Tyrant his wretched life in woful misery. So <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> in the <hi>4th. of Daniel,</hi> for his pride was driven forth of his Kingdom, and constrained to eat grass with the wilde Beasts in the Wilderness. So <hi>Saul</hi> for his pride and disobedience to God, had his Kingdom taken from him, and he in the end most desperately slew himself upon the point of his own sword. So likewise proud <hi>Haman</hi> in the <hi>3d.</hi> of <hi>Esther,</hi> séeking the life of just <hi>Mordecai</hi> and all the Iews, brought himself at last to hang upon his own Gallows, which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self had prepared for <hi>Mordecai.</hi> And as ye heard before, <hi>Jerusalems</hi> pride brought ruins and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction upon their own heads, so likewise the Cities of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> for their pride and contempt of the Lord, were sudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:34793:10"/>destroyed by fire and brimstone which the Lord rained down from Heaven upon them; who as St. <hi>Jude saith, Are by God set forth for example to them that shall yet presume to live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly.</hi> And the whole world except onely <hi>Noah</hi> and his family, were for their pride and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness against God, drown'd by an universal deluge from heaven. So that good King <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> for his pride, in shewing to the Embassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of <hi>Babylon</hi> his riches, and treasuré, for that his sin he lost all his treasure, and his sons also carried captive into <hi>Babylon.</hi> And likewise <hi>David,</hi> who was a man after Gods own heart, for his pride in numbring the people, contrary to the will and command of God, was sadly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished for the same, thréescore and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand of his people being slain with the Pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, as you may read, <hi>2 Sam. 24.15.</hi> So like wise proud <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in the <hi>14th. of Exodus,</hi> for his pride against God in pursuing the chiloren of <hi>Israel,</hi> was drowned in the midst of the Sea he and all his host. And the proud Pharisee in the Gospel justifying himself in his own righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness before the Lord, was for his pride reproved of the Lord and rejected. Se <hi>Herod</hi> in <hi>Acts 12.21, 22.</hi> for attyring himself in sump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous apparel, and not giving glory to the Lord, as it is in the <hi>23.</hi> Verse, immediately saith the Word, the Angel of the Lord salote
<pb facs="tcp:34793:11"/>him, and he was eaten of worms, and gave up the ghost; a fearful example for all proud persons to take notice of. So that wicked <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabel,</hi> of whom you have mention made before, in the midst of her pride and vanities, was thrown out at a wiudow, and dashed in pieces against the ground.</p>
            <p>Many more sad examples I might give you of Gods heavy judgements against proud per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, but I shall conclude all with this one most fearful example, which is as solioweth: A Gentlewoman of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> a very rich Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thants daughter being invited to a Wedding, she thereupon made great preparation for the decking of her self in curious and costly At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre, to which end she curl'd her hair, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her locks, after which she painted her face with sundry oyntments, to make her self séem more beautiful; but so curious was she, that none could he had to make her cloathes fine enough for her: this Gentlewoman being pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her-self up in her glass, could not make her cloathes sit fine enough to her curious san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, at which she being in great rage, began to ban and curse most horribly, casting the cloa hs under her feet, wishing the Devil might take her if over she put on any of them again; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon immediately upon the same, the Devil by Gods just permission, transforming himself in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:34793:11"/>the shape and likeness of a young man, as brave and finical as her self in outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, came in to her, pretending to be a suiter unto her, and séeing her thus passionate, and in such a pelsing chafe, he demanded of her the cause thereof, which she making known to him, he presently destred her to permit him to dress her, promising to her that he would diligently please her in all respects, and thereupon he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to dress and adorn her after a most neat and curious manner, which he soon finished, to her great content and liking; insomuch, that she beholding her self in a glass, as the Devil bid her, became greatly taken and enamoured with her person; after which saluting one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, the devil wrung her neck in sunder from her shouldere, so that she died most miserably, her body which she had before so painted and spot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted being metamorphozed most strangely into black and blow colours, most loathsome to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold; and her face which was before so amorous, became now so loathsome, searful, and deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that it was a most dreadful spectacle to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold; whereupon a rich Coffin was provided by her friends, and her loathsome carkass put therein, and covered over with most rich and costly clothes: at the time appointed for the burial of her vils body, four men immediately assayed to lift up the Corps, but could not possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb facs="tcp:34793:12"/>stir it at all, after which six men assayed to sake it up, but could not once so much as move it from the ground; whereat the standers by greatly marvelling, caused the said Coffin to be opened, add the body of this proud creature being saken away, (none knew how) inslead thereof they found in the Coffin a black Cat, very loathsome and deformed to behold, set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Roff, and crisping and curling of Hair, to the great sear, horreur, and amazament of the beholders.</p>
            <p>Thus Christian Reader have I briefly shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you this sad but true example of Gods wrath against Pride, and having now presented to your view this sad and woful spectacle; my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire and advice if, that all that reads or hears of it, especially all those who delight them in painting and decking themselves up in pride, as this proud person did, that by considering and looking upon this sad example, instead of looking in their own Looking glass, they may behold and sée their own sins, and be ashamed of their evil wayes, for fear lest the same God, who is yesterday and for ever the same, inflict upon them the like, if not more severe punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>O consider this and tremble all ye proud gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, that pin and paint, powder and trim your seldes up in pride and vanity, God hath told
<pb facs="tcp:34793:12"/>you these things to forewarn you: But if you will still persist, and go on in your pride, all these things, and worse then all these shall come upon you and that suddenly, for the mouth of the Lord hath spoken it, <hi>Isa. 23.9. The Lord of hosts hath purposed to stain the pride of all glory, and to bring into contempt all the honourable of the earth.</hi> He hath purposed, and he will do it, unless you repent.</p>
            <p>You have séen now what this sin of pride is, together with the sore evils thereof, and the sad judgements that are threatned against it in the word of God, with the heavy calamities that have befallen Angels, Kingdoms, and persons for this sin of pride: O then I beséech you, and intreat you in the fear of the Lord, as you love your own soule, and as you would not have these sad judgements and calamities befall you, loath this accursed sin and abbor it. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny poor members of Iesus Christ might be fed and cloathed with such things as are daily and hourly néedlessly and superfluously wasted and spent in pride and vanity? I dare boldly say, that there néed not be a poor man or woman in <hi>England,</hi> that should want either food to eat, or clothes to put on, if but the tenth part of what is vainly spent in pride and wickedness, might be spared, and given to the poor. How many thousands are there spent yearly to maintain
<pb facs="tcp:34793:13"/>this accursed and abominable sin of pride? How many are there, that if a poor man want but a penny, or a farthing, will say they have it not? But when the devil prompts them on to pride and to paint themselves, curl and powder their locks, and to spot their saces with black patch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, they can finde money enough. Many there are whose faces God hath made fair and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and yet, as though God hath not done his part by them, or as if they could mend Gods workmanshlp, they spend both their time and Estates to paint and adorn themselves, and thereby become loathsome in the eyes of the Lord; as that accuxsed wretch proud <hi>Jezabel</hi> did, <hi>2 Kings 9.30. Jezabel</hi> painted her face, and tired her head; and she was thrown out of the very window, where she was painting and prank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her self in her pride, and so dashed to pieces against the walls, and trodden under soot to death, and the dogs eat her flesh so that nothing remained of her.</p>
            <p>O that our proud Ladies would think upon this; they that walk upon Belconses, and stand at their doors glorying in their pride and shame, enticing their lovers, by their naked brests and painted saces, to wantonness and lascivious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness: for know this, that your painting, and powdering your locks, and spotting your faces, are but snares and baits for lust and wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:34793:13"/>and that this sin of yours is monstrous and intollerable. I remember a notable story of an ancient man, who comming into <hi>Alexandria,</hi> passed by a woman in a very spruce and wanton dress, whereupon the good old man presently fell a wéeping: And being asked the reason there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he answered, saying, That he wept for two things; first, for the danger that womans soul was in, secondly, to sée what a vilde wretch he had béen, in that he had not taken so much care and pains to serve and please his God, as this wanton woman did to please her wanton lusts and affections.</p>
            <p>I beseech you therefer<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the Lords sake, constder the danger your poor souls are in, and forsake this accursed sin of pride: and for your adorning, let it be such as the Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> commends for your wear, <hi>1 Pet. 3.34. Whose adorning</hi> (saith he) <hi>let it not be that outward a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning of plating the hair, or wearing gold: but</hi> (saith he) <hi>let it be in the hidden man of the heart, even the ornament of a meek and quiet spirit, which is in the sight of God of great price. For</hi> (saith the Apostle in the fifth verse) <hi>after this maner, in the old time, the holy women who trust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in God, adorned themselves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to conclude all, as the Apostle saith in <hi>Rom. 13.14. Let us walk honestly as in the day, not in rioting and drunkenness, hot in chambering
<pb facs="tcp:34793:14"/>and wantonness, not in strife and envy, not in</hi> pride and painting: But as he said, so say I, <hi>Put ye on the Lord Jesus Christ, and make no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision for the flesh, to fulfill the lusts thereof.</hi> O Christians, if you did but know, what a lovely and comely Garment Christ is, I am confident you would cast away all your pride and vanify to put on Christ. Look then upon Iesus Christ with an eye of Faith, through the glass of the Scripture, and sée how this white Garment of Christ doth become you, and forsake all your pride to put on Christ, for I am sure no cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can so wel become a Christian as the white Robes of Christ, which are these, Humility, Temperance, Patience, Vertue, Brotherly kindness, Love and Holiness, which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in the sight of God. To whom be Praise and Glory, both in Heaven and Earth, throughout all Ages; World without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:34793:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>